<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
	<id>cc.arduino.IDE2</id>
	<metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
	<project_license>AGPL-3.0</project_license>
	<name>Arduino IDE v2</name>
	<summary>Open-source electronics prototyping platform</summary>
	<developer_name>Arduino SA</developer_name>

	<description>
		<p>
			NOTE: This wrapper is not verified by, affiliated with, or supported by Arduino. <br/>
			Arduino do not offer official support for the Flatpak wrapper, and so to offer the best support and experience for the Flatpak wrapper please report ALL issues at the Flathub issue tracker (linked by the issue button/link on this page). <br/>
			This allows with issues to be dealt with correctly. For more info press the issues button/link on this page.
		</p>
		<p>
			Arduino is an open-source electronics prototyping platform based
			on flexible, easy-to-use hardware and software.  It's intended for
			artists, designers, hobbyists, and anyone interested in creating
			interactive objects or environments.
		</p>
		<p>
			Included is an integrated development environment that can be used
			to develop and upload code to compatible microcontrollers.
		</p>
		<p>
			The new major release of the Arduino IDE is faster and even more powerful! 
			In addition to a more modern editor and a more responsive interface it features 
			autocompletion, code navigation, and even a live debugger.
		</p>
		<p>
			The Flatpak build of Arduino IDE 2.x requires the user to have USB permissions to upload a sketch, preferably, the user has to be part of the dialout group.
		</p>
		<p>
			Alternatively, add the following 2 lines to /etc/udev/rules.d/50-arduino.rules:
		</p>
		<p>
			KERNEL=="ttyUSB[0-9]*",MODE="0666"
		</p>
		<p>
			KERNEL=="ttyACM[0-9]*",MODE="0666"
		</p>
	</description>
	<releases>
		<release version="2.2.1" date="2023-08-31">
			<description>
				<p>
					Changed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Bump Arduino Firmware Uploader dependency to 2.4.1 (#2206)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Fixed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Fix missing translations for русский and Türkçe (#2201)</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
		<release version="2.2.0" date="2023-08-29">
			<description>
				<ul>
                    <li>fix: name of translation (UA) module [06ad7d1]</li>
                    <li>Updated translation files [b78c462]</li>
                    <li>fix: missing app icon for AppImage on Linux (#2190) [e08439b]</li>
                    <li>chore: bump the version to 2.2.0 [e03e5eb]</li>
                    <li>chore(deps): Use arduino-cli@0.34.0 [b723951]</li>
                    <li>chore(deps): Use arduino-fwuploader@2.4.0 [ea2c54b]</li>
                    <li>fix: falsy context menu handlerId [5fd02b9]</li>
                    <li>Generalize name of "Firmware Updater" [10b3882]</li>
                    <li>Do full run of "Arduino IDE" workflow on tag push [ea91904]</li>
                    <li>fix: do not start obsolete daemon watcher process [57fa18b]</li>
                    <li>fix: execute the Arduino CLI without a shell [2aae9e0]</li>
                    <li>fix: incorrect certificate flashing command string (#2181) [9a99957]</li>
                    <li>fix: handle UNKNOWN code on syscall: 'stat' [b256655]</li>
                    <li>chore(cli): pin version to 0.34.0-rc.1 [420d31f]</li>
                    <li>fix: expand boards if available on detected port [db01efe]</li>
                    <li>build(deps): Bump svenstaro/upload-release-action from 2.6.1 to 2.7.0 [5a76be3]</li>
                    <li>feat: simplify board and port handling (#2165) [69ae38e]</li>
                    <li>chore(deps): Updated to Theia 1.39.0 (#2144) [9a6a457]</li>
                    <li>Clean localization data files before pulling from Transifex [144df89]</li>
                    <li>Add 中文(繁體) ("Chinese (Traditional)") localization (#2151) [e17472e]</li>
                    <li>feat: can dock the monitor widget to the "right" [f6a4325]</li>
                    <li>fix: include all log args in the log message [94d2962]</li>
                    <li>chore(version): updated the version to 2.1.2 [95fdc59]</li>
                    <li>fix(terminal): split-terminal visibility [954fee4]</li>
                    <li>fix(terminal): widget flickering on resize [0bcb182]</li>
                    <li>feat: expose Arduino state to VS Code extensions [42d017e]</li>
                    <li>chore(cli): Bumped the CLI version to 0.33.1 [c66b720]</li>
                    <li>Revert "Revert "chore(cli): Bumped the CLI version to 0.33.0"" [a5c9735]</li>
                    <li>Adjust release procedure and CI system for "trunk-based" development strategy [6e18dca]</li>
                    <li>chore(cli): Bumped the CLI version to 0.32.3 [f3b99b0]</li>
                    <li>Revert "chore(cli): Bumped the CLI version to 0.33.0" [d0bce15]</li>
                    <li>add linux-arm64 to download-ls (#2078) [d79bc0d]</li>
                    <li>fix: warn user when IDE cannot save the sketch [8f8b46f]</li>
                    <li>build(deps): Bump svenstaro/upload-release-action from 2.5.0 to 2.6.1 [d1fa6d4]</li>
                    <li>fix: relaxed saveAll if no Internet connection [4af488b]</li>
                    <li>fix: omit port from upload request when not set [db0049d]</li>
                    <li>chore(cli): Bumped the CLI version to 0.33.0 [0fbd1fb]</li>
                    <li>fix: removed unsafe shell when executing process [9d2297c]</li>
                    <li>fix: remove setting unsafe innerHTML [e47fb2e]</li>
                    <li>fix: show no errors if users cancel lib install [ee43a12]</li>
                    <li>test: use raw core index-update for the tests [31deeeb]</li>
                    <li>fix: do not enqueue write operations on conflict [117b2a4]</li>
                    <li>fix: show notification if lib/core install failed [278dd4b]</li>
                    <li>build: use execa for the packager [36e2092]</li>
                    <li>build: use execFileSync for npm scripts [33ab2a6]</li>
                    <li>chore: updated to Theia 1.37.0 [192aac5]</li>
                    <li>fix: copy when punctuation marks in sketch path [964ea3b]</li>
                    <li>fix: do not exclude cloud sketch diagnostics [e6828f8]</li>
                    <li>test: gRPC core client init integration test [51f69f6]</li>
                    <li>fix: reduced unnecessary GET /sketches request [097c92d]</li>
                    <li>Corrected library.properties assignment w.r.t description and summary [b451e2d]</li>
                    <li>Document 3rd party theme installation in "Advanced Usage" [b3b9494]</li>
                    <li>chore: Updated to the next version after release. [80afd38]</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
		<release version="2.1.1" date="2023-06-30">
			<description>
				<p>
					Fixed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Update Arduino CLI dependency to 0.32.2 to fix arduino/ArduinoCore-renesas#10 (#2121)</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
		<release version="2.1.0" date="2023-04-19">
			<description>
				<p>
					Added:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Allow leading underscore in sketch filenames (#1955)</li>
					<li>Open library examples from Library Manager (#1927)</li>
					<li>Pull and Push icons on editor toolbar when Cloud sketch is open (#1899)</li>
					<li>Use icons to indicate pulled state of Cloud sketches in sketchbook list (#1879)</li>
					<li>Show "[Cloud]" indicator in title of windows with Cloud sketch open (#1878)</li>
					<li>Support pushing local sketches to Arduino Cloud (#1876)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Changed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Base Boards/Library Manager button text on library installation state (#1607)</li>
					<li>Make Boards/Library Manager uninstall interface easier to find (#19)</li>
					<li>Default Boards/Library Manager version menu selection to latest (#1924)</li>
					<li>Improve performance of Library Manager search (#1949)</li>
					<li>Refocus Serial Monitor after verify/upload (#1979)</li>
					<li>Indicate theme type in Preferences menu (#1994)</li>
					<li>Update Arduino CLI dependency to 0.32.2 (#1996)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Removed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Don't offer deprecated themes in Preferences dialog (#1283)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Fixed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Fix Sketchbook view scroll position reverting when selected item scrolled off screen (#1766)</li>
					<li>Fix corruption of multibyte characters in pulled Cloud sketch (#449)</li>
					<li>Fix IDE crash when pushing Cloud sketch (#634)</li>
					<li>Fix incomplete scroll in Serial Monitor after autoscroll enabled (#1736)</li>
					<li>Fix Serial Monitor autoscroll not done for content received when view not in focus (#1724)</li>
					<li>Fix incomplete JSONC support for settings.json (#1945)</li>
					<li>Fix startup fails when arduino.cli.daemon.debug setting enabled (#1942)</li>
					<li>Fix Library Manager version menu change after closure of dependencies installation dialog (#1707)</li>
					<li>Fix Boards/Library Manager entry clipping (#1591)</li>
					<li>Don't offer installation of already installed release in Boards/Library Manager (#781)</li>
					<li>Focus the search field when Boards/Library Manager is opened (#1941)</li>
					<li>Support using debugger with boards platforms installed under non-default data directory location (#1911)</li>
					<li>Fix editor cursor randomly jumping to beginning of line (#437)</li>
					<li>Fix duplicated editor tabs (#1791)</li>
					<li>Focus button in Sketchbook view instead of view container (#1978)</li>
					<li>Show error when monitor process creation fails (#1508)</li>
					<li>Always update themeId settings after theme change (#1988)</li>
					<li>Use appropriate location for manual extension installation folder (#1851)</li>
					<li>Always add #include directive for arduino_secrets.h when pulling Cloud sketches with secrets (#1999)</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.4" date="2023-02-27">
			<description>
				<p>
					Added:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Enable rename and delete of Cloud sketches (#1825)</li>
					<li>Add activity bar icon for Arduino Cloud login (#1877)</li>
					<li>Add support for macOS notarization during local builds (#1916)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Changed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Show custom board option settings in Tools menu (#343)</li>
					<li>Use a local npm registry for app packaging (#1757)</li>
					<li>Always show File &gt; Sketchbook menu item (#569)</li>
					<li>Always show Tools &gt; Port menu item (#655)</li>
					<li>Use more efficient method to get Arduino CLI version (#1572)</li>
					<li>Remove encoding from status bar (#1393)</li>
					<li>Allow addition of existing code files to sketch (#284)</li>
					<li>Communicate cause of debugger not starting with uncompiled sketch (#808)</li>
					<li>Add leading+trailing line break to "Copy for Forum" content (#1859)</li>
					<li>Improve contrast of cursor color in "Dark (Arduino)" theme (#1251)</li>
					<li>Improve contrast of "Output" view stderr text in "Light (Arduino)" theme (#1087)</li>
					<li>Bump Arduino CLI to 0.31.0 (#1921)</li>
					<li>Use hardwareId for board auto-selection (#1913)</li>
					<li>Update translations (#1763)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Fixed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Fix File &gt; Preferences disabled if dialog used soon after IDE startup (#1735)</li>
					<li>Prevent opening of multiple "Preferences" dialog instances (#1735)</li>
					<li>Fix support for user-installed theme extensions (#1742)</li>
					<li>Always set "Updatable" filter when Boards Manager/Library Manager opened from update offer dialog (#1740)</li>
					<li>Fix corruption of multi-byte UTF-8 symbols in Serial Monitor (#589)</li>
					<li>Fix Sketch &gt; Upload/Upload Using Programmer menu items remaining disabled after completion of upload (#1722)</li>
					<li>Fix proxy protocol incorrectly shown as "SOCKS" in "Preferences" dialog (#1775)</li>
					<li>Fix support for SOCKS5 proxy protocol (#1769)</li>
					<li>Fix IDE startup hang if sketchbook folder location not accessible (#1764)</li>
					<li>Update affected UI elements after "Sketchbook location" preference change (#796)</li>
					<li>Update affected UI elements after "Add .ZIP Library..." operation (#659)</li>
					<li>Restart language server after change to platform or library (#670)</li>
					<li>Support IDE installation paths that contain # (#1124)</li>
					<li>Pass custom board option settings to language server (#1029)</li>
					<li>Make File &gt; Sketchbook menu reflect sketchbook folder structure (#1185)</li>
					<li>Populate "Board Info" dialog from port data (#1489)</li>
					<li>Use established sort order in Boards Manager and Library Manager listings (#1106)</li>
					<li>Prevent creation of sketches with non-compliant names (#1599)</li>
					<li>Correct handling of primary sketch tab deletion (#649)</li>
					<li>Fix missing toolbar context menu items when editor doesn't have focus (#1847)</li>
					<li>Fix unexpected sketch deletion when location inside sketch folder selected as rename target (#1882)</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.3" date="2022-12-05">
			<description>
				<p>
					Changed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Switched from arduino.window.zoomLevel to window.zoomLevel preference (#1675)</li>
					<li>Update Cortex-Debug to recent version (#246)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Fixed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Fix editor widget resolving when creating new tab (#1718)</li>
					<li>Fix keybindings to switch between tabs on MacOs (#1685)</li>
					<li>Other ino files are not reflected in the window title (#1656)</li>
					<li>Debugger does not disconnect after stopping it (#995)</li>
					<li>Scrollbar covers bottom line of Serial Monitor output (#1602)</li>
					<li>Problem leaving "focus" mode (#1550)</li>
					<li>editor.hover.delay setting not used by new windows (#571)</li>
					<li>Window title changes to "index.html" during reload (#999)</li>
					<li>Missing translation in Theia's view-container context menu (#1498)</li>
					<li>Indentation guides are always visible (#1613)</li>
					<li>Rightmost tab is selected by default (#643)</li>
					<li>Selecting "New Remote Sketch" from File menu has no effect if "Remote Sketchbook" widget is not open (#1715)</li>
					<li>Serial Monitor sends spurious data (#375)</li>
					<li>Unable to start debugger when watch expressions are configured (#1582)</li>
					<li>Conditional breakpoint only stops the first time (#268)</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.2" date="2022-11-17">
			<description>
				<p>
					Added:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Build IDE2 on darwin arm64 (#1577)</li>
					<li>Create remote sketch (#1580)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Fixed:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Spurious IDE update notifications when using snapshot or nightly builds (#1440)</li>
					<li>Autoformat removes new-line before EOF (#1487)</li>
					<li>"Open Recent" menu missing after recent sketch is deleted (#1596)</li>
					<li>Additional sketches can't be opened via file association/command line argument (#1590)</li>
					<li>"Built-in" examples fail to open with Linux AppImage (#1586)</li>
					<li>"Sketchbook" menu missing if sketch name is invalid regex (#1600)</li>
					<li>First time load of project with many files very slow (#1612)</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.1" date="2022-10-27">
			<description>
				<ul>
					<li>Added: Make links to Boards Manager and Library Manager clickable inside the sketch (#1442)</li>
					<li>Added: Message history in Serial Monitor (#1404)</li>
					<li>Added: Create a custom sketch template for new sketches (#1559)</li>
					<li>Added: Add a project contributor guide (#1419)</li>
					<li>Changed: Can send message to the monitor with Enter (#572)</li>
					<li>Changed: Show user fields dialog again if upload fails (#1386)</li>
					<li>Changed: Update translation files (#1462)</li>
					<li>Changed: Put Arduino libs on top of the Library Manager (#1541)</li>
					<li>Changed: Changed the daemon output from json to text (#1544)</li>
					<li>Changed: Make the "INSTALL" button always visible in Boards Manager and Library Manager (#1568)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Occasional "Unable to watch for file changes in this large workspace" warnings (#39)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Label of unidentified port missing in "Board Selector" after opening new window (#1383)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Bring existing Serial Plotter window to foreground when selected from IDE UI (#1346)</li>
					<li>Fixed: UI unresponsive when sketch has a very long line (#1343)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Align the primary button in all dialogs in IDE (#1368)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Serial Monitor autoscroll only makes bottom line partially visible (#972)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Dialogs UI scalability - Unexpected dialog layouts (#1350)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Color contrast in the Firmware Updater dialog with the dark theme (#1441)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Sketchbook folder not created on startup (#1445)</li>
					<li>Fixed: 3rd party URLs dialog should not wrap text (#1470)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Keyboard bindings do not work properly after change to different keyboard layouts (#989)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Add missing translations (#1431)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Spurious IDE update notifications when using snapshot or nightly builds (#1440)</li>
					<li>Fixed: "Check for Arduino IDE Updates" operation fails when automatic update checks are disabled (#1437)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Avoid intellisense widgets being covered by the bottom panel (#1479)</li>
					<li>Fixed: When opening a dialog, set the focus inside it (#1373)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Attempt to open deleted sketch from Sketchbook or Examples menus fails silently (#53)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Serial Plotter requires \r\n line endings (#1360)</li>
					<li>Fixed: IDE is non-functional if package index can't be loaded (#1084)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Only package indexes should updated after changing the "Additional Boards Manager URL" preference. (#1156)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Application allows setting interface scaling interface past limits (#1384)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Parts of the UI disappear when window is to small (#662 #1515)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Incorrect spacing of the horizontal rules in the editor hover (#1503)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Sort Board selection menus like as described in the platform's boards.txt configuration file (#802)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Intermittent failure to recognize ports (#573)</li>
					<li>Fixed: The style of the buttons in the library installation dialog break when the labels are too long (#1314)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Uploading disabled without port selection (#702 #770)</li>
					<li>Fixed: Opening invalid sketch via file association/command line fails silently (#964)</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.0" date="2022-09-14">
			<description>
				<ul>
					<li>The moment you (and us) all have been waiting for has arrived. Let's all welcome the official, stable release of Arduino IDE 2.0. This new IDE provides a modern user interface thanks to its responsive interface, as well as a completely overhauled backend supplied by the Arduino CLI. We hope you'll enjoy it as much as we enjoy bringing it to you. Yours truly, Arduino Team</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
	</releases>

	<screenshots>
		<screenshot type="default">
			<image>https://github.com/arduino/arduino-ide/raw/main/static/screenshot.png</image>
			<caption>Image of Arduino IDE v2</caption>
		</screenshot>
	</screenshots>

	<url type="homepage">http://www.arduino.cc/</url>
	<url type="help">https://docs.arduino.cc/software/ide-v2</url>
	<url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/flathub/cc.arduino.IDE2/issues/35</url>
	<url type="translate">https://www.transifex.com/arduino-1/ide2/</url>
	<url type="donation">https://www.arduino.cc/en/donate/</url>
	<content_rating type="oars-1.0"/>
</component>
