<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
	<id>cc.arduino.IDE2</id>
	<metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
	<project_license>AGPL-3.0</project_license>
	<name>Arduino IDE v2</name>
	<summary>Open-source electronics prototyping platform</summary>
	<developer_name>Arduino SA</developer_name>

	<description>
		<p>
            		Arduino is an open-source electronics prototyping platform based
            		on flexible, easy-to-use hardware and software.  It's intended for
            		artists, designers, hobbyists, and anyone interested in creating
            		interactive objects or environments.
		</p>
		<p>
            		Included is an integrated development environment that can be used
            		to develop and upload code to compatible microcontrollers.
        	</p>
		<p>
			The new major release of the Arduino IDE is faster and even more powerful! 
			In addition to a more modern editor and a more responsive interface it features 
			autocompletion, code navigation, and even a live debugger.
		</p>
		<p>
			The Flatpak build of Arduino IDE 2.x requires the user to have USB permissions to upload a sketch, preferably, the user has to be part of the dialout group.
		</p>
		<p>
			Alternatively, add the following 2 lines to /etc/udev/rules.d/50-arduino.rules:
		</p>
		<p>
			KERNEL=="ttyUSB[0-9]*",MODE="0666"
		</p>
		<p>
			KERNEL=="ttyACM[0-9]*",MODE="0666"
		</p>
	</description>
	<releases>
		<release version="2.0.0" date="2022-09-14">
			<description>
				<ul>
					<li>The moment you (and us) all have been waiting for has arrived. Let's all welcome the official, stable release of Arduino IDE 2.0. This new IDE provides a modern user interface thanks to its responsive interface, as well as a completely overhauled backend supplied by the Arduino CLI. We hope you'll enjoy it as much as we enjoy bringing it to you. Yours truly, Arduino Team</li>
				</ul>
			</description>
		</release>
	</releases>

	<screenshots>
		<screenshot type="default">
			<image>https://github.com/arduino/arduino-ide/raw/main/static/screenshot.png</image>
			<caption>Image of Arduino IDE v2</caption>
		</screenshot>
	</screenshots>

	<url type="homepage">http://www.arduino.cc/</url>
	<url type="help">https://docs.arduino.cc/software/ide-v2</url>
	<url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/arduino/arduino-ide/issues</url>
	<url type="translate">https://www.transifex.com/arduino-1/ide2/</url>
	<url type="donation">https://www.arduino.cc/en/donate/</url>
	<content_rating type="oars-1.0" />
</component>
